We've got all the regular scheduled meetings in my city council from Monday, November 7th, 2022.
Two public input and scheduled personal appearances.
We have none.
Three consent agenda staff recommends we approve items four and five.
Six budget amendments.
23-10.
A capital and procurement project.
This is the same one you approved on the MSUA.
The money is coming out of capital improvement,
which is a city fund going to the MSUA funds.
We've got to approve it on both sides.
Same, $2,940.
Thank you.
7.
Presentation of the Mike Signar Award.
The Kevin Browning.
My Mr. Beckagin.
Projects.
First of all, set in with a picture.
Turn a lot of these props or something that we don't want to do.
The great lead agency, presentation of flood map and flood survey, Mr. Beckett-June.
I won't keep you very long.
I just really wanted to tell you a few things.
We were really blessed with some great advice and a great deal of preparation and developing
this flood map that we have shared with you and we have additional flash drives for any of you that
might want to have one just of your own.
We did have the project, we got more than we wanted with the project.
We asked the thriving earth exchange, which is part of American geophysics union, to help
us develop a map that citizens in Miami could use if they were new here.
They moved in and might not know how to get out of town if waters rose and they weren't familiar.
What we did not know that the woman preparing the map would do was really prepared for the
whole county.
So the first time we saw this, we were really surprised when you see the left side of this picture
and you've got the city really unendated.
We always knew it felt like that but we really had never seen it.
And then we looked farther up the map and could actually see what was coming at us and that would be the chat pile sitting in the floodplain.
All these years I had never known that because all of those roads are flooded, you can't go there and see that they're sitting out there in there.
So I'd never seen it and maybe you have, maybe you've seen drone footage or aerial photos, but I had not.
And so it just both of these images were really what struck us in the urgency that you're facing right now in what's coming to you.
And so our once again our goal was to to look very carefully at this the city and and wonder what else we could do is a nonprofit, how can we help the city, how can we help the county, how can we help look more deeply it is what it's what what's happening here.
And so we partnered with two other agencies, buy in and in collaboration and with them we developed a flood survey and the survey is one that we're going to begin.
And actually we launched it at the conference a couple of weeks ago.
But we'll begin walking the neighborhoods in the 1% floodplain will be walking the neighborhoods will be knocking on doors will be following up with sailors to those people that we miss will follow up with emails if we have them.
We're going to reach out to everyone not only in the Miami floodplain that you that you've got that you're dealing with, but but also those in.
And there may be other parts of the county that we may also.
Try to survey but the survey is one that we developed that we believe the information that we get from that will help you in the future as you're looking at what do people really want and what do they need and what have they experienced.
And so I didn't bring handouts for all of you on.
that but I'll just look over a few of these items that will be asking. We're asking permission
from the people that fill out the survey to be able to share their information with the
city if they give permission for us to share it. We will keep much of this will go into
a data set that will put together for you. The other thing that happened recently is that
we received a $50,000 grant to work on data and so we'll be able to do the survey and
then also help you understand it. In ways we'll help us understand it also but also for
you to have that information. We're going to ask just simple things on when was your house
build? We're going to ask please circle the years that your house was flooded and how many times
did the home receive damage of those times? How many people live in your home and how how do you
do you have your plan for evacuation? Do you basic questions on do you currently have flood insurance?
If you do not, why not? What steps have you taken to address the flooding issues of your own home?
As simple as parking your vehicle somewhere else? All of these kind of minute details on how people
deal with the floods when they're dealing with each one? How do you find out about the flood level? When do you know you should
move on? Would you be interested in a buyout if you had one? Are would you like adaptations so that you
can stay in your home? Would you mind building your house up? It may be that you have a garage if you just had
water proof blockage there? You might save your house. There may be some adaptation that you
could do and so we're looking for that because you need to know that as you look for.
How do you deal and how do you help people that are facing a flood?
So we believe that what we've got will be a great interest to you.
And I would like to ask that you encourage people to fill it out.
When we contact them, if they don't hear from us right away, if they want to come by, we can fill that out at our home.
At our office. If they want to do a phone interview, we can do that also.
But we believe that these answers will help the city.
And because we will face another flood.
And one of the last questions on here was I'll read it to you.
Well, couple, what is your opinion about the Grand River Dam Authority's decision to raise the water level of grand-like of the Cherokees?
And it's just a simple support that idea or oppose it.
The only thing that we're going to add there is some lines for just their thoughts to be really recorded if they'd like to share them.
The other question we have on here is the other project that we're doing.
And that is an oral history project that we're working with Oklahoma University to do.
It's called Air Water and Work.
So of course the water may be flooding, but it also may be fishing.
So if you go out there and get a spoon bill, we may want your story.
You may want to sit for one of those interviews.
But also with work, work is also what you're doing now.
People that have worked at Beeth Goodrich.
We have work kind of in a race to catch those people and capture those stories.
And one of the questions on here, would you like to be part of that oral history project?
So anyway, I'm with you.
And also open this up if there's questions you have or any wishes, any other kinds of things you'd like us to look at.
Yeah, everything we get we're gonna be able to share it in some way with you. We won't have names attached to that kind of question
But you know, we'll be able to do that. Yeah, um, yes
I did want to show you just a couple of more images.
There's more dams.
This was a really tremendous dam that we noticed two weeks ago, and it's about maybe 500 feet north of the air.
And this dam was built not by children.
The rocks are entirely too big.
They could not have done it.
And so we broke the dams, so water could pass through.
The water, north was really pretty black.
And we broke it through.
And when we were, you could see black coming through.
And that concerned us.
And so the next Monday, the DEQ came and looked it over.
They, it's probably some of the discharge from the commerce discharge that they're allowed to do.
Got caught up here in turn to black.
But we let it, we let it, we let enough through that it wasn't a violation.
Anyway, that's the letter I got today.
They didn't exceed their limit of what they can send down.
So just another reason why the dams here are harmful to people and the environment.
When you trap bad water, you're just going to get worse water.
So anyway, just wanted to show you that.
The water did was black all through town.
Image, I'd like to show you that I don't know if I have it.
I was going to go over how to use the map.
But you probably already know how to use maps.
But we have on the flash drive tutorial in case people that have not ever used a map could, could use it.
Just how the, how the legend on it works, what that means and the little stack that there's, there's extra stuff there to see.
And then they're, and how do, how do you zoom in on it in now?
We just wanted to let people that.
really haven't manipulated a map, know how to do that. And then also that you can see both
both kinds of maps you can see a Google map, what that looks like, but also a street version.
And all the different layers that you can do, you can turn the flood on and off so you can see those layers go away and you see.
Anyway, the other images that I would hope that you will look for when you're looking at that flood map are the images of the DECU's indication of which yards have been cleaned up. We have a layer of that on here. So you can look, there's also because both note is something on it.
So we've updated the property owners on there. And we'll keep trying to update that as often as we can. So that'll be another layer that you can use on the DECU's.
On their site, if you click on those, each one of those properties, it doesn't give a name, it just gives the location of that property.
The other two layers that are, I think, are very striking are the 2007 flood images. And thanks to the work Gina Manders did in working with Julie Mathews at the time.
They were able to, and I'm not sure who else helped with that. Anyway, in 2007 really mapping that flood.
And you'll see blue dots and those are all the yards that we're able to get a permit to rebuild and then another layer with all the red dots those homes during the 2007 flood that weren't given permits to rebuild.
And so I'm hoping that we add those additional layers of other years of flood because I think that that information will be very valuable to the city to see how many other permits were given during other years.
So thank you very much for the time I didn't mean to talk so long. But we're, we're, it's dire, you know, when you start looking at what we already are facing.
And so the other thing that we'll be doing is doing these two images as postcards and we'll
probably have a thousand of those made.
We'll probably walk the Christmas parade and see if anybody wants to send one with their
own messages on there.
I think some of these you'll be able to circle where you lived in those floods or where
how close you are to a flood, so those messages, the other thing that we are hoping to
help coordinate with you all or whoever else that would like are those messages to
furg to say exactly what happened to you, what you saw happened, what did you experience?
Are individuals in town?
We do, in May, I'd like to reiterate, that the importance of that and we've actually had
previous furg employees tell us that that is important, that not necessarily having
a form letter that everybody just signs their name to and it regurgitates the same message
over and over again because it's not about the volume, but it literally is about telling the
individual stories, that means a lot in that actually resonates with furg employees, so I can't
encourage that enough that it's important that people tell their story.
Right, right, right, right, well if you have additional folks that want to help us walk
neighborhoods where we're willing to take them, we really think that it's one thing to be flooded
but it's one thing to think nobody cares, our nobody is listening and so I think through
asking people their individuals opinions and what's happened to them, but off.
also encouraging them to share their voice.
And so we'll do that with this blitz of emails
because I believe that's one of the venues,
but I think we're gonna mail postcards to you.
They're gonna have an opportunity
because you might have a 12 year old story,
but you might have a later story too.
I think you can have multiple stories
and multiple losses and multiple things to say.
And you can't put it all in one.
So let's wrap it fire them.
Yeah, and more than once, you know,
every opportunity that we can find.
And so the longer stories will collect
in our oral history project.
And, yeah, but the shorter ones we need to blitz.
So any other questions are concerns,
which is, okay, thank you very much for the time.
Okay, so what we are talking about
is the Aglease in the around the airport or the city side.
We have another Aglease that we'll talk about
at a later time that's in my PFA owned,
but this is just the city lease.
If you look at this map, kind of confused me at first
because I thought C's just for city
when I saw this the first time years ago,
it actually stands for crops.
So those are the properties that our contractors,
our farmers are putting croupland.
using for croupling.
We got two bidders this year.
One was from Zach Rendell, who currently has the lease.
And the other one was from Rick Wilson,
who currently has the mowing and bailing lease,
which is different.
It's just more like a vegetation.
We can control the vegetation by allowing people
to come in and hay those areas
around the airport to meet FAA requirements,
because you can't have growth more than several inches high.
So I provided you with an aerial shot of the airport land,
so you can kind of see the areas that are used for croupling.
They look very different than the areas that are mowed or bailed.
Do you have any questions about this?
These are revenue-generating contracts.
They pay us to use the land.
So is that something that goes out public for anybody else
to fill their name in a hat?
Yes, it's advertise.
I need to remind the council to turn their mics on.
I'm getting a message from Keith that he can't hear us.
I'll re-estate my question.
Are these contracts that are put out for public to bid on?
And anybody who wants to be a part of this could be?
Yes, it's published in the local newspaper.
It's placed on our website, and I have a list of previous farmers.
Anyone who's ever expressed interest in mowing, bailing,
using our land for agriculture purposes.
So if they get an email, as well, to let them know.
So two bids, while we got them, wasn't so pretty kind of dry-wring.
Yeah, I mean, based on the numbers, this is the best offer.
And he's done an excellent job.
I haven't heard any complaints.
Yeah, and he's got a good idea.
So what happens to the 6500 a year?
It goes into the airport.
There's an airport line item for...
OK, don't get it.
Yes.
would not interfere with any of the plans that their board has in the future, the near future.
There is a clause in the contract that says that we can, we can take back use of the property in any point.
This is property, he's least before, right?
We've been leasing this property for as long as I've been involved in purchasing.
And I think Randall has had it for the past five years.
And honestly, that was my first bid for that.
In my first or second year is when it came up.
The other one, the 2201, you said that.
We're going to look at that at another time.
The other one?
Yes, it's the one that's in my PFA.
So I still have the same bid date that we opened.
We opened it.
We bid them an open them on the same day.
That's what we're proving that.
Then I mean, I do that.
Thank you.
William.
Hi.
Marker.
Thank you.
I'm 12.
A award-least purchase agreement to bank a grant-lake for the payment of the wheel loader.
C22-68 and three police vehicles.
C22-62.
Thank you.
Related signing.
The payment authority to the city manager or his designate.
So these are actually police vehicles.
I apologize for my confusion previously.
But these are police vehicles.
There are three of them.
And then another wheel loader separate from the first one.
This one is a street.
He's equipment.
Wheel loader.
It looks like a tractor with a big scoop.
It's a big front and lower the twist in the middle.
Yep.
I actually looked it up, so I could answer that question.
The last one was used up.
When we talked about it, our last meeting, yes.
This one is going to be held by the Street Department.
So again, we put bids out.
I have a mailing list of banks for financing.
And there is several posted in our website.
It's in a blanket email.
And we got three responses on this one.
And the bank of Grand Lake had the best rate.
Apparently, I got in just like minutes before the rates went up.
And just to remind our, these are budgeted items approved in the budget.
We've just found the best financing that fit the budget expense expenditures for the
year.
That's in order.
It's 2022-14, a minute, chapter five aviation, article two, airport authority board, section
five-two-seven membership of the code of ordinances, providing severability, providing for conflicting
provisions, fulfilling all conflicted ordinances and establishing an effective date.
Thank you, Mayor.
This is the ordinances.
It stops there for a board.
We've actually had problems sitting in the board.
Previously, it was three people from, in our four people in town, three from county.
And we've had just issues, five people live in town that are involved or cared about their
board.
It would be a good advisory board.
We have several board chairman, they have had during choir, doctor Stewart.
They all live just around the county.
So we want to mend that to live or work in our county or in our living or our own county
and work in our own.
Also, we have people that are involved in our airport, however, points there, that we can
get a very pool for our airport board.
We've asked Ben to draw this off, and this is our recommendation for the mayor, for council.
The other major change in this ordinance, way I read right now, a majority of the board is appointed
in one year, and that did not seem like a real wise decision.
So we've spread it out to where it's a three-year cycle, same as what the ordinance was.
was, but two in one year, two in another year,
and then three instead of four being a majority.
Those are the basic changes of what this does.
And that speaks to all the appointments that we have.
That is the majority of all airport members.
There's one new one that will be appointed.
The rest are all the current board.
And just reappointing them for their current term for their terms.
So a little bit about that, through a clerical error,
we were appointing people for four-year terms,
and that's not what the ordinance currently provides,
know what the revised ordinance does.
So the reason we're going to go through the reappointments
is to get everybody back on the three-year cycle,
which are the next several agenda items.
So you got six new, and then you got one more,
and then you got four-year, and then you got four-year.
We do them all.
Well, the next one is emergency.
I'm going to take them out.
Okay.
So there's a number of four-team emergency calls for that same one.
So we just, just, move to the group.
Then there's a couple of people.
Hi.
15.
There's an automation to re-appoint that jerk's buyer to the airport authority board.
Time to expire 11, 7, 25.
So mayor of this, and they're following a couple of agenda items.
Which could all be considered together, if you so desired,
it's to get all of those board members on the proper cycle,
now that our new ordinance is in place.
15.
20.
Motion to approve.
15.
Second.
No point.
Be set up.
Williams.
All right.
21.
Mayor's.
Information to avoid.
Let's parker to the Monium Industrial Public.
Facilities Authority in the MiPFA.
Climding by 117, 23.
幼稠指.
Yeah.
So what we found out is that everybody that was on the MiPFA.
Zee-the-dad or their term has ended.
Oh, I'm not sure I want that.
Why is there?
The problem is that the MIPFA is still being...
connecting business, even though there is no board that is actively overseeing that business.
And so this agenda and the next couple of agenda items would be to appoint the five of you to be the board for MIPFA so that we can at least ratify everything that's hopefully we can ratify everything that's been done.
And we're trying to figure out what all exactly has been done, but we want to make sure that it's done legally.
And then ultimately we don't know if this is going to be one of the trusts that we recommend to you be dissolved or not.
But if it is going to be dissolved we still have to have a board that is able to transfer the property that it owns and take care of the rathing up the business of the MIPFA.
So this is intended to be an interim step to protect yet the property that it owns and the city.
So it's not asking me if this is where to make it.
So 21 be the marriage appointment myself.
Do they might be FAA?
Most two proof.
I can.
September 5th.
One.
Twenty-two marriage nominations.
Two.
Twenty-three.
There's almost a point.
Brad Williams.
The MIPFA.
Most two proof.
Five.
Seven.
Twenty-four.
There's almost a point.
Kevin Duckel.
The MIPFA.
Most two proof.
Seven.
Twenty-five.
There's almost a point.
One.
Twenty-two.
We find ourselves with three primary goals that we set out to achieve with this salary study.
The first was to complete a salary study with an outside consultant to get their expertise.
and allow them the time and opportunity together
the data that we needed.
And then ultimately to make recommendations on how
we utilized the 282,000 that the board had agreed
to budget towards these merit increases in adjustments
resulting from the salary study.
And then thirdly to develop a long-term plan
for the employee salary that places employees
in the correct position within their current pay bans.
Because as we suspected, we knew that we were going
to be severely outside of our pay bans
based on market study and do work.
So essentially what we've gleaned from the study
or what gouged or his gleaned from it.
Gouged did receive survey results from, well,
we had Barsville Bixby Clairemore, Greenpool,
Joplin.
We also asked my public schools in the Peoria tribe.
We also got some information from Wagner,
and then we got additional information from five OML
municipalities that participated in a no-mail study,
the O Oklahoma Municipal League.
So we really feel like we got a good baseline of data.
And what we found out is that we needed to make these shifts,
the percentages of increase in the bans range from anywhere
from 2.39% below market to around 19.09% below market.
So some were pretty significant.
Now if you recall, in back in January,
the council had approved us to go ahead and make a preliminary adjustment
of one of our lowest pay bans, our A-band,
where we basically increased from $11 to $13.
That was back during a time in which most races were struggling
to hire.
We were struggling like anyone else,
and we knew that the $11 base minimum was way below our market.
And of course, that came back as well,
and it wasn't appropriate move, and luckily, we had already done that.
My little thing about what's the problem of our positions.
About six units of weight have done.
He has basically utilized $1,000 to apply to the police
that scored above.
the police to the wedding came in as if there's a fake couple who worked there for him to walk
this through and sitting there and taking their recommendations and then we kind of get a lot
of back to the walk back in the park to do I think we said a place to play in the place of
police and the correct decision to bring in space on a year to the wall of the youth and spending
that I present that of you could be there will be adjustments and on going to the
event that all of you did a bit of a place to have something to prepare for you
it was not to be faced with a couple who used so expensive our police are very fast
and it doesn't matter how many large front wheel loaders we don't usually save with them in the
front space inside the youth so it takes place and so we save money there that's going to
I'm really excited about what this allows us to do
So with these changes have you seen the turnover and the turn slow down and the retention pick-up?
The mayor is wanting to affect July 1st. I mean, we just recently did it, but they, they went back rough-drove, but the stuff for the salaries are ready.
We'll go into effect with this upcoming payroll.
What's the name of the company?
The regulations that we process, and the previous year's current year's, you've got in the big half of the thing you want to say.
Utilize more and more.
So all the boys will have it up to you to put it in put in into that.
Are they going to get a reminder at the end of the year or something like...
whatever you did that's awesome time brain learning of it there's a lot of things it
it'll let us do in-house sarvex and if we want to set some levels of some
merit metrics for them to reach it it it's really easy to set up and it's easy to
date and then it tracks them and there's the reporting so it's nice
Any questions for us in your boat?
Getting a great job, send me.
Thank you.
All right.
27.
New business, sir.
Either is written since the posting of this agenda, mayor, and council, community announcements.
I haven't picked out your clothes.
I just got one.
The Mama High School FFA program, they have an instructor that is really taking that thing
to do heights.
So I want to congratulate them on the efforts.
He has him as a top 10 FFA in the nation.
Pretty significant.
Because I know we weren't anywhere near there when he took over, but when an outstanding job
he's done, him as wife, I think, but doing outstanding job with kids and other kids are really
loving it.
So I want to give a shout-out to them and congratulate them on their efforts.
I really excited about which is really easy today to prepare for all of this.
I'd like for maybe we can get in here one of these days to talk to us a little bit, but let's
know what they're doing.
If I need anything, must.
What do we do?
What else?
Point nine.
City Manager Communications.
Thirty adjournment.
I'll move.
Thank you.